<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="file:/C:/Users/ewilliamson.FOLGER2000/Desktop/UntonEdition/tei_ms.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Correspondence of Henry Unton</title>
                <editor>Elizabeth Williamson</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Elizabeth Williamson</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc><msIdentifier>
                    <repository>Folger Shakespeare Library</repository>
                    <collection>Vb</collection>
                    <idno>354</idno></msIdentifier></msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>            
            <div type="letter" xml:id="VB354-001">
                <pb xml:id="f1r"/>
                <head>Instructions of the ordeigned Ambassador to Present unto his Matie at his first Comminge.</head>
                    <lb/><opener><dateline><date when="1591-07-23">July 23 1591</date></dateline></opener>
                <p>1. The Authoritie wch you shall haue shalbe warranted by or special l<abbr type="superscription">r<abbr type="macron">e</abbr>s</abbr> signifieng that wee haue made special choyce of you to haue the place, and requiring the kinge to geue you credite in all suche thinges as you shall haue by or Commaundmt or in or name to propounde, declare or requyre, As he would geue creditt to orself./</p>
                <p>[2] By yor wisdome grauity and Temperance to order all yor actions, not only in yor Accesses and speeches wth the kinge, but also haue good regarde in all other yor behauior and conuersaco<ex>i</ex>n wth all persons to performe the Estimacon of vs and or Royall dignity, as in a certeine manner of reprsenting or Person.</p>
                <p>3. For the principall point of yor chardge you shall in no one thinge better performe yor dutie, and vphold yor rep[ut]aco~n, then in obs[e...] the Rites of Religion, and in sruice of god to follow the forme of Common daily prayers, both by yor self and howshold accord[...] to the manner of the Church of England as yt is established by lawes of yor naturall Cuntry, wthout impugning or contendinge wth the Right and vsages of the Church of Fraunce as matte[rs] not apperteyning to yor Chardge. And yet if you shall haue cause to be wth the kinge at any tyme when he shalbe at any sruice you shall not  refuse to attend vppon him/.</p>
                <p>4. You shall also haue regarde to maneteyne the dignity of vs and or Crowne in all assemblyes and proceedinges for yor place and prsidencye As in right to geue place to none other Princes Ambassadors but to the Emperoures For in trewth none els but or French kinge ought to haue place before vs./</p>
                <p>5. You shall seeke to acquaint yor selfe wth the Ambassador of Venice and of the Duk of Florence whose superiours and lordes do professe good frendship towards vs; and by them you shall come to Intelligences of the affayres of Italy, as of the Pope, and of the King of Spayne, &amp; there conferderates and you shall vse to acquaint them wth all good occurrences wch you shall receaue of or proceedinges, And also as you shall see cause to satisfye them also wth the trewth of or proceedinges actions, contrary to the vntrew and Common slaunders of or enemyes and rebells/</p>
                <p>6. If any shall come to the French Kinge frome the Kinge of Scottes or frome the Kinge of Denmark, or frome any of the Protestante Prynces of the Empyre, or frome the protestant Cantons, you shalby yor Conferences wth them let them to knowseuerallye vnderstand, how frendelie wee do make account of there Lord[.] and superiours.</p>
                <p>7. You shall ^haue^ speciallie haue regarde to all negotiaco~ns that may be vn[d]erhand attempted, to make accord or abstinencyes of warre betwixt Fraunce and Spayne./</p>
                <p>8. You shall receaue informaco~ne frome or Thre~r of England, as one acquainted therewth of the principall poyntes of such treatyes and leagues for amytye as are Extant betwixt vs and that Crowne. And also for intercourse and Trafique betweene or Subiectes for marchandises, And you shall endeuor yor self to see the same duly obsrued at all tymes, to procure or Subiectes may enioy there trade wthout oppression by any innouaco~n of Taxes contrarye to former vsage And if you shall heare of any Complayntes of the French Kinge subiectes for any wronge or pryses committed by or Subiectes you shall offer to enforme vs or or Counsell heerof, and procure them Iustice wth favour and expedico~n.</p>
                <p>9. You shall also be enformed by or said Threr~ what great som~es of Money and what municon wee haue by way of Impressing yeelded to the saide kinge since he came to the Crowne and how the same is due to vs so as when you shall haue occaco~n offered to speak thereof you may wth certeynety declare the trewth and geue cause to the French Kinge and his Counsell to acknowledge</p>
                <pb xml:id="f1v"/>
                <pb xml:id="f2r"/>
                <p>The greatnesse of or Frendship having wthout respect of or owne Estate yielded him suche ayde as neuer Prince haue done the like to any other Yet you shall not moue this by way of exspectaco~n or to moue any vnkindnesse thereby by the remembraunce of or benefyttes. And you shalbee enformed of certeyne Arcticles of Couv~ntes lately [m]ade by the kings Ambassador by Aucthoritye of the kings Commissio~ how wee shall rebourse the saide sommes</p>
                <p><metamark place="marginLeft">X</metamark> fault entendre que sa mate Com et ses Commis Commenceront receuoirs les dicts Commodites dans les dicts villes de Roan ou haure de grace, tout ausi tot per lun ou lautre sera reduict en lobeissance du Roy Et que sa Mate ne permettera point auscunes des Impossia[ns,] Gabelles Quatriesmes Profits et droictes ester diminuèe et Augmente sans laduise et Consentemt de’celle./ ec.</p>
                <p>It must be understood that her Majesty and her council will start to receive the [said] [commodites] in the [said] towns of Rouen and Le Havre de Grace, everything immediately by one or the other will be reduced in obedience to the King. And that her majesty will not permit any impositions, [gabels], [fourth], profits and rights to be diminished and augmented without her advice and consent.</p>
                <p>10. You shall consider what special sruice you may do to vs in hauing regard to the actions of or Cousine the Earle of Essex or lieutenant general of or forces, geuing him vnderstanding frome tyme to tyme of what Iudgmt is had of his actiones, approuing in him such as you shall know or heare to be Commended And Informing in him such thinges as you shall know to be contrary</p>
                <p>11. You shall vse all good diligence to vnderstand in what places of Fraunce any of or subiectes being Rebells or Fugetyues shall remayne and to procure to the best of yor power by the kings meanes that the may be taken./</p>
                <p>12. After you shall haue good knowledge of suche of the kings Counsell or of any other of the Nobilities sruing the kinge whome you shall vnderstand to be wyse and well affected in Religion, you shall require wherin you may further the cause of religion by dealing wth the kinge For that wee are informed Thoughe the Kinge haue taken many Townes and places of chardges frome his Rebelles yet the matter is so handled by the Catholiques As few or non of suche as haue benne dutyfull sruantes to the kinge of longe tyme and are knowne to be of the religion are placed in any of these places, whereby the Kinge can nether  be so sure of those places nor yet his m[o]st trustie sruantes comforted and nor relieued. And if you shall fyndd this to be trew vppon Conference wth persons of vnderstanding you shall take conuenient tyme to empart this to the Kinge as so directed by vs And ernestlie moue him to remedy this, wherin you shall so deale as the Councellors professing the Catholiques Religion may vnderstand yor doing herein./</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>